None of us like to contemplate
わたしたちはだれも
重大な事故に遭ったり—
being in a serious accident or receiving news
命を脅かすような
重い病気と診断された時のことを—
that we have a very serious illness
that may even be life threatening.
考えたいとは思いません
When the blood issue also arises,
at such times,
しかし そうした状況で
血の問題が起きる場合—
もちろん忠節を保ちたいと
決意するでしょう
of course we’re all determined
that we’re going to keep our integrity.
But we also feel the need
for comfort and for support
しかし 信仰にとどまれるよう
慰めや支えも必要です
so that we can remain faithful.
Now, Jehovah never promised
for this period of time
エホバは今の時代—
奇跡によって病気を回復させるとは
保証しておられません
that we would receive miraculous healing.
But he did promise that we would receive
something very significant.
しかし とても重要な あることは
約束しておられます
Would you open your Bibles with me?
ご一緒に聖書を開きましょう
Let’s look together at Psalm 41:3.
詩編 41編3節です
こうあります—
“エホバご自身が病の床にある
彼を支えてくださいます”
It says: “Jehovah will sustain him
on his sickbed;
during his sickness
you will completely change his bed.”
“あなたは彼の病気の間—”
“そのすべての寝床を
必ず替えてくださいます”
Well, now, The Watchtower, back in 2008,
the September 15 issue,
この聖句に関して—
「ものみの塔」
2008年9月15日号に—
just made a nice little comment
on this verse.
興味深いコメントがありました
It said:
“David did not expect Jehovah
“ダビデはエホバが奇跡によって
病気を取り除いてくださるとは—”
“to perform
a miracle and remove [his] sickness.
“期待していませんでした”
“Rather, David felt certain
that Jehovah would ‘sustain him’
“むしろ エホバが
「自分を支えてくださる」—”
“つまり病床にある自分を支援し—”
“—that is, give him support and strength
“力を与えてくださることを
確信していたのです”
while he was lying on his sickbed.”
Well, that’s what Jehovah has promised.
これがエホバの約束です
He’s promised that he’s going to provide us
with the support and the strength
エホバは
わたしたちが忠節を保てるよう—
支えと力を与えてくださるのです
that we need
so that we can keep our integrity.
Well, Hospital Information Services (HIS)
here in Brooklyn,
ブルックリンのホスピタル･
インフォメーション･サービス—
the Hospital Information Desks
at each of the branches,
各支部の医療機関情報デスク—
and the Hospital Liaison Committees (HLC)
各国の医療機関連絡委員会は
血の問題が起きる時—
have been very powerful tools
in the hand of Jehovah
このエホバのみ手による
支えと力を与えるために—
to provide this support and strength
非常に力強い働きをしてきました
when the blood issue arises.
Did you know that now worldwide
世界にはおよそ1700の
医療機関連絡委員会があり—
there are some 1,700
—that is 1,700—
1万3000人以上が奉仕していることを
ご存じでしょうか？
Hospital Liaison Committees
with over 13,000 members?
This is not easy work.
簡単な仕事ではありません
The vast majority of these brothers
are not physicians;
兄弟たちの多くは医師ではなく
医療機関とのコネも全くありません
they’re not connected
to the medical community in any way.
Often, they have to get up
in the middle of the night
兄弟たちは病院に行くために
よく深夜に起こされます
to go to the hospital.
Sometimes they deal
with very confrontational situations.
時には非常に難しい状況もあります
Usually all of the situations
that they deal with are emotionally charged.
彼らが対処する状況の多くは
緊迫したものです
Their work is very seldom seen by others.
他の人から働きが見られることは
ほとんどありません
注目されることはないのです
They are not in the spotlight.
Well, when we reflect on the work
of these wonderful brothers
これら素晴らしい兄弟たちが—
他の人たちに援助や支え
助けを与えるため—
who are willing to accomplish this work
喜んで果たす奉仕について
思い巡らすと—
of giving assistance and
support and help to our brothers,
エレミヤ 23章のエホバの言葉が
思い浮かびます
we can’t help but think of this scripture
in Jeremiah chapter 23,
エレミヤ 23章4節—
“「そして わたしは彼らを
実際に牧する牧者たちを—”
where Jehovah says—
Jeremiah 23:4:
“彼らの上に起こす”
“‘And I will raise up over them shepherds
“彼らはもはや恐れることも
恐怖の念を抱くこともなく—”
“‘who will really shepherd them.
“‘They will no longer be afraid
or be terrified,
“だれひとり失われないであろう」と
エホバはお告げになる”
and none will be missing,’
declares Jehovah.”
Well, that’s exactly
医療機関連絡委員会は
まさにこのことを行なっています
what the Hospital Liaison Committee
brothers do.
彼らは必要な情報や支えを
与えてくれる—
They are wonderful shepherds
who are there to help the brothers
素晴らしい牧者たちなのです
to have the information
and the assistance they need
それによって兄弟たちは
忠節を保つことができるのです
so that they can maintain their integrity.
I recall one experience when I was working
わたしがカナダの医療機関情報デスクで
働いていた時のことを—
with the Hospital Information Desk in Canada.
A sister in a northern Canadian city,
お話ししましょう
北部の街で ある姉妹が
大きな事故に遭いました
she had been very, very seriously injured.
She had to be airlifted to a larger center
集中治療を受けるため—
高度医療センターに
ヘリで搬送されました
where she would be able to receive
more intensive care.
A Hospital Liaison Committee member
was immediately notified;
すぐに医療機関連絡委員の兄弟に
知らされ 兄弟は病院へ行きました
he went to the hospital.
And so, as soon as the aircraft landed
ヘリが到着し 姉妹が降ろされ
病院に担ぎ込まれると同時に—
and the sister was being taken off
and wheeled into the hospital,
兄弟も病院の玄関に到着しました
there the brother was waiting in the hallway.
And so, when he approached her
lying on the stretcher,
姉妹の横たわるストレッチャーに
近づくと—
姉妹は恐怖で震えていました
the sister was trembling with fear.
Well, when he looked down at her,
のぞき込むと 姉妹は兄弟を見上げ
she looked up and she said,
“Are you a doctor?”
「お医者さんですか？」と尋ねました
And he said,
“No, I’m your brother.”
「いいえ あなたの兄弟です」
Well, immediately the sister
すると姉妹は フーッ
—this huge sigh of relief
because now there was someone
必要な助けを与えてくれる兄弟がいて—
ホッとため息をつきました
who could give her the practical help
that she so much needed.
Well, what are some of the ways
この取り決めによって与えられる
実際的な援助には—
that this arrangement
does provide practical support?
どのようなものがあるでしょうか？
Well, I’m not sure if you know this,
but at 89 branch offices around the world
ご存じかどうか分かりませんが—
米国とカナダを含む
世界の89の支部には—
—including the United States and Canada—
we have brothers who are on call
医療機関連絡委員会や
エホバの証人に—
24 hours a day, seven days a week
無輸血治療を行なうための
援助を求める医師からの電話を—
to answer calls
from Hospital Liaison Committee members
年中無休24時間体制で
受ける兄弟たちがいます
and also from doctors
who request assistance
on how to treat Jehovah’s Witnesses
without the use of blood.
This is an amazing arrangement.
これは驚くべき奉仕です
When I worked with HIS,
HISで奉仕していた時
兄弟姉妹やHLC—
I recall many times
in the middle of the night,
we would receive calls
from a brother or a sister
切実に助けを必要としている
医師からの電話をよく深夜に受けました
or from an HLC or from a doctor
about someone who
was desperately in need of assistance.
And the organization
had provided such wonderful tools.
また 組織には
素晴らしいツールがあります
For example,
a database has been assembled
例えば—
信頼できる医学雑誌から取られた
何千もの文献のデータベースがあります
of literally thousands of medical articles
from respected medical journals.
Now these articles can be sent
to a doctor or to a medical team,
これらの文献は医師や
医療チームに送られ—
and they explain very specifically
無輸血で治療を行なうには
どうすればよいかを—
明確に説明するものとなっています
what can be done to address a situation
without the use of a blood transfusion.
Often, when a doctor
receives an article like that
医師はそのような文献を受け取ると
同僚が書いたものだったり—
—he sees it’s from one of his peers,
it’s been published in a respected journal—
権威ある雑誌から取られていることに
気づくので—
he is much more willing to cooperate.
より協力的になってくれます
And also, he sees
in a practical way what can be done.
そして 自分もできると
理解してくれます
But even better,
each Hospital Information Desk
さらに 各医療機関情報デスクには—
maintains a list of consulting doctors.
協力的な医師のリストが
保管されています
Now, these are
very well-respected physicians
彼らは権威ある医師たちで—
who are not afraid
to confer with other doctors
とても複雑で困難な症例でも
無輸血で治療を行なうことを—
and explain to them how
even very complex, very difficult cases
他の医師と協議したり
説得したりすることに慣れています
can be managed without the use of blood.
I recall one time in the middle of the night,
ある日 わたしが深夜に
電話を受けると—
we received a call about a sister
who had just given birth,
出産の時に大量出血した
姉妹に関する情報が飛び込んできました
and she had lost
a significant amount of blood.
The doctor managing her case
was very interested in receiving help.
担当した医師は
切実に助けを必要としていました
Well, we called
a very, very well-respected professor
わたしたちは
カナダで非常に権威ある—
協力的な産婦人科の教授に
電話しました
of obstetrics and gyneocology
in Canada
who was always willing
to provide assistance.
わたしは第一声—
Well, I started off the call by saying,
“真夜中に電話して大変
申し訳ございません”と言いました
“I’m so sorry to call you so late at night.”
Well, the doctor said:
“Please don’t apologize, Mark.
すると教授は—
“謝らないでください マーク”
I’m always happy to do anything
I can to help the sisters.”
“いつでも姉妹たちを助けられて
嬉しいです”と言われました
Well, of course,
he was not a Witness himself.
もちろん 教授は証人ではありません
But he viewed those dear ones
as his own sisters,
しかし自分の姉妹のように
見てくださり—
助けたいと願ってくださいました
and he was willing to help them.
Well, such courageous and skilled physicians
all around the world
このような
勇敢で熟練した医師たちが—
世界中で大勢の兄弟たちを助けています
have done so much to help our brothers.
And the tools just keep on improving.
ツールも改良し続けています
Many of you may know
皆さんもjw.orgにある—
that now we have a section
for medical professionals
「臨床医のための医学情報」サイトを
ご存じでしょう
on our jw.org website.
Now, I’ll reiterate:
繰り返しになりますが—
This is not a site or an area
for Jehovah’s people;
このサイトはエホバの証人向けでは
ありません
it’s specifically designed
for medical professionals.
医療の専門家向けのサイトです
But that area,
最近作られたものですが
既に素晴らしい成果を挙げています
although it’s only recently been established,
is already having a wonderful effect.
Let me relate this experience.
経験をご紹介しましょう
A sister wrote this into the branch.
ある姉妹が書かれたものです
She said: “Recently my husband took me
to the emergency room,
“最近 夫と救急病院に行き—”
“and we discovered
I had a mass of some sort near my appendix
“わたしの盲腸の近くに
大きな腫瘍が見つかって—”
“and that a huge
and possibly messy surgery
“とても難しい手術が必要だと
言われました”
“was needed to discover the problem.
“When I told the surgeon
that was assigned to me
“担当した外科医は
わたしがエホバの証人であり—”
“that I was one of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
“妥協しようとしないので
動揺されました”
“he became agitated when I reinforced
“my nonnegotiable stand.
“He never became rude or harsh,
“医師は取り乱しませんでしたが
とても困惑していました”
“but I could tell that he was very troubled.
“My husband left
to make a phone call to the brothers.
“夫は兄弟と電話をしに
席を外しました”
“Five minutes later,
a resident came to tell me
“5分後に研修医が来て—”
“さっきの外科医がjw.orgで
情報を見に行ったと伝えました”
“that the surgeon
had just gone to the jw.org website
“and was downloading information.
“We had never mentioned the website.
“ウェブサイトについては
話していませんでした”
“How he knew or who told him,
we’ll never know.
“どこでどうやって知ったかは
分かりません”
“But ten minutes later,
he came back with copies of the information.
“10分後 外科医が情報を印刷して
戻ってきました”
“He had read it,
he had marked the pages,
“それを読んでしるしをつけ—”
“わたしたちと共に
内容ひとつひとつを網羅しました”
“and he went over everything
with my husband and me.
“Then he took my hand, and he smiled.
“そしてわたしの手を取って
微笑みました”
“He asked if I was ready,
“準備はいいかと尋ね—”
“わたしのためにベストを尽くすと
約束されました”
“and he promised to do his very best for me.
“He said he too had made
“彼も生涯妥協しないことを
神に誓っていたそうです”
“some nonnegotiable decisions
with God in his lifetime.
“He saw me about 12 hours after the surgery,
“手術の半日後 わたしはその医師に
問題がなかったかと聞きました”
“and I teased him about being a trouble.
“He said, ‘No, it was extraordinary.’
“「いいえ
大変素晴らしいものでした」”
“We know he meant what he had just learned
“その答えから
医療機関連絡委員会や—”
“about the Hospital Liaison Committee
“エホバが備えてくださった情報が
医師の役に立ったんだと分かりました”
and Jehovah’s provision
for information for His people.”
The sister concluded by saying,
姉妹は結論でこう述べています
“I have never felt
such a wave of peace from Jehovah
“真理のうちに歩む人生の中で—”
“エホバからの平和を
これほど感じたことはありません”
in all my years in the truth.”
Well, Jehovah did not promise us
エホバは奇跡的に病気を回復するとは
約束しておられませんが—
miraculous healing at this time,
but he did promise
that he would provide us
支えと力を与えると保証しておられます
with support and strength
when we are sick.
What a beautiful gift Jehovah
has given his people
医療機関連絡委員会の良い働きは—
エホバからの素晴らしい贈りものです！
through the fine work
of the Hospital Liaison Committees!
Truly, this has been
a strengthening aid for us
それでわたしたちはこれからも
次の指示に従ってまいりましょう
“to keep abstaining from . . . blood.”
“血[を]避けなさい”